Finding Aid for Alexander Winchell Papers, 1833-1891
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Writings and lectures
  - 1855, 2 folders
    - The great work of Prof. Agassiz (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, Aug. 21)
    - Stratigraphical geology or, Classification and mineral characteristics of the strata composing the earth's crust (Box 8)
      (Lecture I, Detroit, Aug. 28)
    - Palaeontological geology, or, Fossil characteristics of the strata of different ages (Box 8)
      (Lecture II, Detroit, Aug. 30)
    - Economical geology, or, The connexion between geological science and the industrial arts (Box 8)
      (Lecture IV, Detroit, Sept. 1)
    - The Shell marls of Michigan (Box 8)
      (Sept.?)
  - 1856, 1 folders
    - Notes on the geology of middle & southern Alabama (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, Aug. 14)
    - On the origin and age of the red loam of Alabama with a notice of a loess deposit on Prairie Creek in Greene Co. (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, Aug. 15)
    - Statistics of some artesian wells of Alabama (Box 8)
      (Sept.)
  - 1857, 2 folders
    - Popular education (Box 8)
      (signed "Scholasticus", Michigan, March)
    - The Nature of "hair worms" (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, May 17)
    - The Relation of mind to the soil (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, Sept. 23)
    - Classification of the animal kingdom, exhibiting all the principal groups of animals as for the genera ... (Box 8)
    - Grammatical principles of scientific nomenclature (Box 8)
      (undated)
  - 1859, 1 folders
    - Dr. S. P. Duffield's lecture in Ann Arbor (Box 8)
      (Ann Arbor, March 3)
    - The Geological history of animal life (Box 8)
  - 1860, 1 folders
    - Notes on the geology of the Lower Peninsula of Michigan (Box 8)
      (St. Louis, undated)
    - The Cycles of matter, or, The Permanence of the Earth & the destiny of the race (Box 8)
      (Aug.)
  - 1861, 1 folders
    - The Cycles of matter, or, A Glimpse into the future ages (Box 8)
      (Ann Arbor, Nov. 8)
  - 1862, 1 folders
    - Genera of coral-producing loantharia occurring fossil in the United States (Box 8)
      (Jan. 14)
    - Synopsis of bryozoa (Box 8)
      (Jan. 17)
    - Remarks on a section of the rocks of Michigan prepared for Prof. J. D. Dana (Box 8)
      (Mar. 24)
    - Notice of the rocks lying between the carboniferous limestone of the Lower Peninsula of Michigan, and the limestones of the Hamilton group ... (Box 8)
  - 1862-1864, 1 folders
    - Voices from nature (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan)
  - 1863, 1 folders
    - On the grading of Sunday schools, with a review of Dr. Floy's text books (Box 8)
      (June 9)
    - On the origin of the prairies, and the absence of trees from their surface (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, June 15)
    - Notice of a gar pike supposed to be undescribed (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, June 22)
    - Observations on the slug fly of the cherry and pear with notes on its embryonic development (Box 8)
      (University of Michigan, June 23)
  - 1864, 1 folders (Box 9)
    - Notice of Dr. Tappan's pamphlet (Box 9)
      (Ann Arbor, Mar. 31)
    - Determination of the magnetic meridian (Box 9)
      (University of Michigan, Nov.)
    - Sur les relations zoiques d'ischadites Murchison (Box 9)
      (University of Michigan, Dec. 15)
  - 1865, 1 folders
    - Sur les affinit zoiques d'ischadites Murchison (Box 9)
  - 1866, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - 1866, Christian theology illustrated from nature and from science (Box 9)
      (Oct. 7)
    - A General classification of the animal kingdom, embracing both the recent and the extinct forms (Box 9)
    - A System of natural theology (Box 9)
    - Conspectus of the animal kingdom (Box 9)
      [former v. 199]
  - 1867, 2 folders
    - Christian theology illustrated from nature (Box 9)
      (Northwestern Christian advocate, Jan. 2-July 17) [former v. 225]
    - The Human soul considered in the light of nature (Box 9)
      (Ann Arbor, Mar.)
  - 1868, 1 folders
    - The Geological foundations of our state (Box 9)
  - 1869, 5 folders
    - The Cycles of matter, or, Glimpses into the past and future (Box 9)
      (Valparaiso, Ind., Jan. 1, and other places and dates)
    - Syllabus of a course of lectures on geology, to be delivered in the University of Michigan in the months of March, April and May, 1869 (Box 9)
    - Sketches of creation (Box 9)
      [omitted chapters] (May 1)
    - The Stone folk (Box 9)
      (Ann Arbor, Oct. 16, and other places and dates)
    - Geological lectures (Box 9)
      [outline] [former v. 195]
  - 1870, 2 folders
    - A Key to the geological chart (Box 9)
      [2 drafts] (undated)
    - Lectures on geology (Box 9)
      [outline] [former v. 196] (microfilmed)
  - 1871, 3 folders
    - Scientific education (Box 9)
      (Wesleyan University, July 18)
    - Kakistocracy, or, The Rule of the rabble (Box 9)
      (Mattoon, Ill., Dec. 4)
    - The Marshall group: a memoir on its geological position, characters and equivalencies in the United States (Box 9)
  - 1871-1872, 2 folders
    - [Drafts of chapters relating to the existence of God] (Box 9)
  - 1872, 1 folders
    - Kakistocracy, or, Too much popular government (Box 9)
      (University of Michigan, Mar. 13)
    - Poem delivered at the quarter-centennial jubilee of the Class of 1847 of the Wesleyan University (Box 9)
      (July 15)
  - 1873
    - Remarks to the medical graduates (Box 9)
      (Feb. 12) (microfilmed)
  - 1874, 1 folders
    - Syllabus of a course of lectures on geology to be delivered in the Syracuse University during the winter term of 1874-5 (microfilmed) (Box 9)
  - 1875, 1 folders
    - Geological lectures (Box 9)
      [outline] [former v. 197] (microfilmed)
    - Supposed agency of ice-floes in the Champlain Epoch (Box 9)
  - 1876, 2 folders
    - The worth of culture (Box 9)
      (Vanderbilt University, June 20)
    - The beautiful (Box 9)
      (State Female College, Memphis, Tenn., June 14, and other places and dates)
    - Observations on the Chautauqua conglomerate (Box 9)
      (Aug.) (microfilmed)
  - 1877, 1 folders
    - Consequences of the doctrine of the derivative origin of species (Box 9)
      (Syracuse University, Winter Term)
    - Adamites and preadamites (Box 9)
      (First M.E. Church, Syracuse, Dec. 11)
  - 1877-1879
    - Intellect and religion (Box 9)
      (unpublished book-length manuscript, 5 folders)
  - 1878, 1 folders (Box 10)
    - Culture and knowledge (Box 10)
      (Universalist Church, Syracuse, Nov. 4)
    - A plea for modernized education (Box 10)
      (Academy of Music, New York, Dec. 24)
  - 1880, 2 folders
    - Preadamites (Box 10)
    - Religious doubt (Box 10)
      (University of Michigan, Jan. 25)
  - 1881, 1 folders
    - Some thoughts on planetology (Box 10)
      (Apr.)
    - Martha's Vineyard Summer Institute (Box 10)
  - 1883, 1 folders
    - The use of the microscope in geology (Box 10)
      (Feb.)
    - Secular increase of the Earth's mass (Box 10)
      (published Dec. 28)
    - Scribner's Where did life begin? (Box 10)
      [book review] (undated)
  - 1884
    - Revisions and additions for new edition of Johnson's Natural history (Box 10)
      (published 1884)
  - 1885, 1 folders
    - Identification of rocks (Box 10)
    - Scheme of undergraduate geological study (Box 10)
  - 1886
    - Modern writings bearing on the relations between intelligence and religion (Box 10)
      (published Jan.)
  - 1887, 1 folders
    - The "Huronian system" (Box 10)
      (Ashland, Wis., July 31)
  - 1889, 1 folders
    - Man's position in Nature's plan (Box 10)
      (Lecture 1 of Religious truth in scientific lights) (Hamilton, N.Y., Apr. 15)
  - 1890, 1 volumes; 3 folders
    - Preadamites (Box 10)
      (revisions for 1890 edition)
    - The religious sense in the light of science and philosophy, or, God in spontaneous thought (Box 10)
      (Lecture 3 of Religious truth in scientific lights) (Colgate University, Apr. 14)
    - A key to the scientific nomenclature (Box 10)
      (May 15) [former v. 200]
    - Nature's ways to God, or, God in reflective thought (Box 10)
      (Lecture 4 of Religious truth in scientific lights) (undated)
  - Undated
    - Outline of a work on Intellect and religion, also titled Archaeus, or, God in nature (Box 10)
      [not the same as the 1877-1879 manuscript with similar title] [former v. 226]
    - Untitled draft of book on natural history (Box 10)
    - Writings relating to education, 1 folders
      - Organization of an American university (Box 10)
      - Principles of conation and subordination of higher studies (Box 10)
      - The rights of geology in education (Box 10)
      - Salem Summer School of Science (Box 10)
    - Writings relating to science
      (1 folder)
      - Analogical evidence (Box 10)
      - Barrande versus Darwin (Box 10)
      - Boston lectures and other papers contributed toward a reconciliation of religion and science (Box 10)
      - Difficulties of development theories (Box 10)
      - Hints for a text book in astronomy (Box 10)
      - Structure and homology of the siphon in Endoceras (Box 10)
    - Writings, Miscellaneous
      - Something curious (Box 10)
      - Themes for Christian contemplation (Box 10)
      - Untitled Commencement (?) address (Box 10)
      - Untitled lecture on water (Box 10)
      - What is the state? (Box 10)
    - Fragments (Box 10)
    - Lecture materials
      - Notes, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Notices (Box 10)
      - Proposals and exhibit schedules (Box 10)
  - Notebooks
    - General [or General geology]
      (also titled Scientific papers: consisting of miscellaneous scientific investigations not including the natural history of Michigan since 1858, nor anything in the character of field notes)
      The General notebooks include chiefly geological and paleontological papers not concerning Michigan.
      - Vol. 3 1857 February-1866 March (Box 10)
        [former v. 186]
      - Vol. 4 1866 April-1888 March (Box 11)
        [former v. 187]
      - Vol. 5 (Box 11)
        [former v. 188]
      - Vol. 6 1888 March-1890 December, 1887 February-1889 August (Box 11)
        [former v. 189]
    - Michigan
      also titled The natural history of Michigan: being a digest of observations made at various times since 1858
      The "Michigan" notebooks include most of Winchell's writings on topics relating to Michigan.
      - Vol. 1 1859 February-1865 August (Box 11)
        [former v. 183]
      - Vol. 2 1865 December-1881 January (Box 11)
        [former v. 184]
      - Vol. 3 1881 January-1890 May (Box 11)
        [former v. 185]
    - Popular
      also titled Miscellaneous papers: consisting or essays, addresses and letters on various subjects not of a scientific character
      The "Popular" notebooks include Winchell's writings relating to religion, evolution, and education (including geological education). Vol. 16 of this last group (Box 14) includes collected historical materials on the University Musical Society.
      - Vol. 1 1865 July-1867 February (Box 12)
        [former v. 204]
      - Vol. 2 1867 February-1870 September (Box 12)
        [former v. 205]
      - Vol. 3 1871 April-1875 May (Box 12)
        [former v. 206]
      - Vol. 4 1871 October-1872 February (Box 12)
        subtitled Archaeus, or, God in nature [former v. 207]
      - Vol. 5 1875 May-1877 January (Box 12)
        [former v. 208]
      - Vol. 6 1877 January-1879 May (Box 12)
        [former v. 209]
      - Vol. 7 1877 August-1880 August (Box 12)
        subtitled Religion and intelligence, Intellect and religion [former v. 210]
      - Vol. 8 1878 October-1879 April (Box 13)
        subtitled Preadamites [former v. 211]
      - Vol. 9 1879 June-1881 March (Box 13)
        [former v. 212] [includes autobiographical sketch]
      - Vol. 10 1881 February-1882 October (Box 13)
        [former v. 213]
      - Vol. 11 1880 August-October (Box 13)
        subtitled Intellect and religion, vol. 2 [former v. 214]
      - Vol. 12 1882 November-1889 February (Box 13)
        [former v. 215]
      - Vol. 13 1883 October-1884 November (Box 13)
        subtitled Geological excursions, or, The rudiments of geology for young learners in geology [former v. 216] [also includes editorials prepared for the Fortnightly index]
      - Vol. 14 1884 November-1885 April (Box 13)
        subtitled Elements of geology for high schools, colleges, normal and other schools [former v. 217]
      - Vol. 15 1884 November-1889 September (Box 13)
        [former v. 218]
      - Vol. 16 1881 April-1889 November (Box 14)
        subtitled The University Musical Society and its subordinate organizations [former v. 219]
      - Vol. 17 1885 December-1886 February (Box 14)
        subtitled Walks and talks [former v. 220]
      - Vol. 18 1889 October-1890 October (Box 14)
        [former v. 221]
  - Poems, 1844-1872, 1 folders; 2 volumes (Box 14)
    [former v. 231-232]
- Reference and research files
  The Reference and research files series (Boxes 14-19) contains a wide variety of material from all periods of Winchell's life, arranged by topic. The materials in this series include Winchell's notes on reading and on scientific observations, transcriptions of the writings of others, and miscellaneous material. The chief topics included (among many others) are:
  - Amenia Seminary: "The Literary harvest" 1843 (Box 14)
  - Anthropology (Box 14)
  - Field book "Alpha" 1876 (Box 14)
    (contains notes relating to preadamites) [former v. 194]
  - Preadamites, by Edgar Conkling 1873 (Box 14)
  - Astronomy 1847-1850 (Box 14)
    (contains calculations of eclipses)
  - Autographs, 1 folders; 2 volumes (Box 14)
    (1 v. is autograph book of Jennie Winchell) [former v. 246 and 280]
  - Botany
    - Catalogue of plants found growing without cultivation in the state of New York, copied from Torrey's Flora of New York, 1850 (Box 14)
    - Herbal register 1850-1852 (Box 14)
      [former v. 198]
    - Santa Cruz mosses, undated (Box 14)
      (dried moss specimens)
    - Miscellanea (Box 14)
  - Calculating books, 2 volumes (Box 14)
    [former v. 201-202]
  - Chemistry (Box 15)
  - Education (Box 15)
  - Figuring book (Box 15)
    v. 2 only
    [former v. 203]
  - Geological Society of America, 1888-1890; 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 15)
    [former v. 269]
  - Geology
    Geology, which includes notes from various geological expeditions in Alabama, Michigan, and West Virginia, Winchell's bibliography of references to geological publications, and the results of a survey on geological education in Michigan schools.
    - Alabama (Box 15)
    - Dictionary of crystallography and physical mineralogy (Box 15)
      [card file, in Box 24]
    - Estimates for outfit in geology, zoology & botany, 1876 (Box 15)
    - List of rock formations (Box 15)
    - Michigan
      - Magnetic springs (Box 15)
      - Salt (Box 15)
      - Stratigraphy (Box 15)
      - Survey results, Geology in the schools of Michigan, 1888 (Box 15)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
    - Petrographic notes circa 1880s (Box 15)
      [former v. 192]
    - Questions for geological sketches (Box 15)
    - References on American geology 1818-1865 (Box 15)
    - Synopsis of the rocks, 1877 (Box 15)
    - Tables of rocks (Box 15)
    - West Virginia (Box 15)
    - Miscellanea, 4 folders (Box 15)
  - History (Box 15)
  - House
    [see also oversize folder (Ac)]
    House, which includes information about the construction and landscaping of Winchell's octagonal house, built where Hill Auditorium now stands in Ann Arbor.
    - Account book 1859-1887 (Box 15)
      [former v. 253]
    - Building memoranda, plans, and Miscellanea (Box 15)
  - Kentucky University, student register, 1868 (Box 15)
    [former v. 240]
  - Laboratory equipment (Box 15)
  - Languages
    - German (Box 15)
    - Hebrew (Box 15)
    - Italian (Box 15)
      [former v. 230]
  - Library
    - Account book 1859-1888 (Box 15)
      [former v. 235]
    - Catalogue 1852 (Box 15)
      [former v. 233]
    - Desiderata (Box 15)
    - Notes (Box 15)
      [former v. 228]
  - Masonic University, tuition record, 1853 (Box 15)
  - Mathematics (Box 15)
  - Mesopotamia Female Seminary, course of study, 1851-1852 (Box 15)
  - Meteorological observation
    Meteorological observations includes what Winchell elsewhere described as a complete collection of meteorological observations taken in Michigan from 1823 to 1869, as well as observations he made in Alabama and New York and records of another observer in Sarnia, Ontario.
    - Alabama (Eutaw), 1850-1852 (Box 15)
    - Michigan (multiple stations)
      - Temperature, cloudiness, and precipitation, 1823-1869 (Box 16)
      - Winds 1831-1869 (Box 16)
      - Miscellanea (Box 16)
    - New York (Amenia)
      - 1849-1850 (Box 16)
        (also includes Eutaw, Alabama, 1851, and Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1854)
      - 1850 (Box 16)
    - Ontario (Sarnia) 1854-1855 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous stations (Box 16)
  - Meteorology (not including observations) (Box 16)
  - Michigan Geological Survey
    Michigan Geological Survey files includes business records of the survey (daily journal, lists of applicants, reports, and miscellanea); field notes of A. D. White, A. E. Dolbear, E. A. Strong, and A. S. Wadsworth while working on the survey; reports of A. O. Currier and J. B. Steere on their work for the survey, and drafts of Winchell's survey reports, including the never-finished 1871 final report of the survey (which contains a report on Michigan forests by C. B. Headley).
    - Business memoranda 1869-1871 (Box 16)
      [includes daily journal, lists of applicants, reports, and miscellanea] [former v. 178]
    - Records
      - 1859
        - Biological observations (Box 16)
        - Field notes of A. D. White (Box 16)
          [southern Lower Peninsula]
        - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
      - 1860 (Box 16)
      - 1861 (Box 16)
      - Undated 1859-1863 (Box 16)
      - 1869
        - Field notes of A. E. Dolbear (Box 16)
          [Grand Traverse Bay region]
          (also includes field notes, 1870, of S. R. Winchell [Delta County])
        - Field notes of E. A. Strong [Grand Rapids region] (Box 16)
          [Manistee/Ludington region]
        - Field notes of A. S. Wadsworth (Box 16)
          [Manistee / Ludington region]
        - Report of A. O. Currier (Box 16)
          [Higgins Lake / Muskegon River region]
        - Report of J. B. Steere (Box 16)
          [Indian mounds in Montcalm County]
        - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
      - 1870
        - Field notes of A. S. Wadsworth (Box 16)
          [eastern Upper Peninsula, statistical information for northern Lower Peninsula towns]
    - Reports
      - 1859 (Box 16)
        draft
      - 1860 (Box 16)
        draft index
      - 1869 (Box 16)
      - 1870 (Box 16)
      - 187
        (planned final report) draft
        - Part 1 (Box 16)
          (Physiographic features of the state), Book 1 (Geographical position and area), Chapters 1-5
        - Part 1 (Box 16)
          (Physiographic features of the state), part of Book 6 (Vegetation), "Michigan forests", by C. B. Headley
        - Memoranda (Box 16)
          [includes outline and notes] [former v. 182]
        - Outlines, 2 folders (Box 16)
          [includes former v. 181]
    - Tabular resume of Michigan Geological Survey field work, 1859-1860; 1869-1870 (Box 16)
      [former v. 179]
  - Michigan Journal of Education 1859-1860 (Box 16)
  - Michigan State Teachers' Association 1858-1859, 2 folders (Box 16)
    [includes former v. 243]
  - Mining, 1880s (Box 16)
    [chiefly concerning Gogebic Iron Range investments]
  - Music (Box 16)
  - Natural history (Box 17)
    - Catalogues and report to accompany the objects of natural history collected mainly in the vicinity of Eutaw, Greene Co., Alabama and presented to the museum of the Smithsonian Institution, 1852-1853 (Box 17)
    - Permanent list of works on natural history circa 1855-1872, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 17)
      [former v. 234]
    - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
  - Newbern Female Academy, advertisement, 1850 (Box 17)
  - Paleontology
    The Paleontology files include Winchell's notes on the classification of fossils.
    - Bibliography of the fossil mammals of the United States 1868-1875 (Box 17)
      [former v. 25]
    - Description and classification of fossils
      - Brachiopoda, undated (Box 17)
      - Crinoidea (Palaeozoic) 1864 (Box 17)
        [former v. 191]
      - Stromatopora undated (Box 17)
        [former v. 190]
      - Tetrabranchiata 1876-1877 (Box 17)
        [former v. 193]
      - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
        (2 folders)
    - Lists of fossils (Box 17)
    - Notes and references (Box 17)
    - 1845-1851 1854-1859 (Box 17)
      (also includes journal entries) [former v. 251]
    - Day book 1851-1854 (Box 17)
      [former v. 252]
    - Ledger 1858-1887 (Box 18)
      (actually a journal)
      [former v. 254]
    - Personal memoranda 1855-1863, 2 volumes (Box 18)
      [former v. 249-250]
    - Study memoranda 1869 (Box 18)
      [former v. 222]
  - Photography (Box 18)
  - Physics (Box 18)
  - Plantation documents (Box 18)
  - Political economy (Box 18)
    [former v. 229]
  - Publishing accounts (Box 18)
  - Science and religion
    - Evolution (Box 18)
    - List of works bearing on the interrelations of religion and intelligence 1885 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Scientific notebook 1881 (Box 18)
    [former v. 227]
  - Sermons, 1847-1848 (Box 18)
    [former v. 74]
  - Soils (Box 18)
  - Student registers (consolidated) 1854-1890, 2 volumes (Box 18)
    [former v. 237, 278] (microfilmed in part)
  - Syracuse University
    - Bylaws draft 1874 (Box 18)
    - Inaugural speeches 1873 (Box 18)
    - Reports 1873-1875 (Box 18)
  - Testimonials and reviews (Box 18)
  - Topography
    Topography includes collected data on the elevation of many points in Michigan and surrounding states, as well as tabulations of Michigan islands, lakes, and townships, and collected information about roads, canals, and harbors. The elevation data may be of particular interest because of the large number of precisely located place names associated with the elevation figures.
    - Catalogue of maps and profiles of public works (rail roads and canals) found in the office of the Secretary of State circa 1870 (Box 18)
    - Elevation data for places in Michigan and surrounding area, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Great Lakes water levels and soundings (Box 18)
    - Magnetic data for places in Michigan and surrounding area (Box 18)
    - Michigan canals and harbors (Box 18)
    - Michigan islands (Box 18)
    - Michigan lakes (Box 18)
    - Michigan roads (Box 18)
    - Michigan townships (Box 18)
    - Michigan triangulation (Box 18)
    - Topographical data for Michigan and the Northwest circa 1870s, 4 folders (Box 18)
  - University of Michigan (Box 19)
    University of Michigan file includes Winchell's statements to the Board of Regents concerning important issues facing the university and information about the University Musical Society and University Museum.
    - Cumerian Club, undated (Box 19)
    - History of the controversy about Dr. Houghton's field notes, 1858 (Box 19)
    - Museum
      - Catalogs of specimens (Box 19)
      - Descriptions of Trowbridge collection and White collection 1863, 1859 (Box 19)
      - Draft reports 1863, 1869-1871 (Box 19)
    - Statements to the Board of Regents 1854-1868 (Box 19)
    - Student registers 1861-1870, 1881-1890, 5 volumes (in 2 folders) (Box 19)
      [former v. 238-239, 241-242, 279]
    - University accounts 1871-1873 (Box 19)
    - University Musical Society and Choral Union, 1879-1890 (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 19)
  - Vanderbilt University
    - Rules of the Biological Laboratory, undated (Box 19)